<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<article>
  <title>Contributors</title>

  <para>This project would not be possible without the help of many 
  individuals and institutions.</para>

  <bridgehead id='ohchr'>OHCHR</bridgehead>

  <para>First and foremost, many thanks to the United Nations and the
  <ulink url='http://www.ohchr.org/EN/UDHR/'>Office of the High
  Commissioner for Human Rights</ulink> for gathering so many
  translations and inspiring this project.</para>

  <bridgehead id='translations'>Translations</bridgehead>

  <para>Many thanks to all the folks who helped with the translations; in no particular order:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Denis Moyogo Jacquerye for help with many translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>xekri, for corrections to the Japanese (Osaka) [jpn_osaka] translation.</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
      <para>Corey Garrett, for corrections to the Wolof [wol] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Sovichet, for corrections to the Khmer [khm] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Simas, for corrections to the Lithuanian [lit] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Steve White, for corrections to the Malayalam [mal], Ossetin [oss], Krio [kri], Hindi [hin], Kannada [kan], Bengali [ben], Bhojpuri [bho] and Magahi [mag] translations; and for reporting the incorrect HTML generated by empty &lt;title> elements.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>David Mediavilla, for reporting errors in the Asturian [ast] translation, and the absence of notes for the Romanian (2006) [ron_2006] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Nicolas Stefanovitch, for the conversion to Unicode of the Nenets [yrk] and the Gilyak [niv] translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Titus Wormer, for fixes to the Mizo [lus] and Khasi [kha] translations.</para>
    </listitem>


    <listitem>
      <para>Boyd Kelly, for reporting errors in the Jula [dyu] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Elad Segev, for reporting errors in the Hebrew [heb] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Ivan Derzhanski, for reporting that the [prq] translation is a duplicate of the [cbs] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Johannes Neumeier for corrections to the Chinese, Wu [wuu] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><ulink url='http://rosettatype.com'>Rosetta Type</ulink>for corrections to the Croatian [hrv] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Natia Bagbaia and Connie Bobroff for major corrections to the Georgian [kat] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Aiśwarya KK for corrections to the Malayalam [mal] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><ulink url='http://www.globalbility.org'>Globalbility Togo</ulink>, for the Tem [kdh] translation (see the <ulink url='s/status_kdh.html'>status and history</ulink> for a detailed report of the translation process) and the Moba [mfq] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Federico Campagnolo of the Academia de ła Bona Creansa for fixing the Venetian [vec] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Benny Lin for transliterating the Javanese translation from the Latin to the Javanese writing system [jav_java].</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Srinidhi A for corrections to the Kannada [kan] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Shriramana Sharma for corrections to the Tamil translation and for the Sanskrit (Grantha) [san_gran] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Saadat Mateen, Rabee and Riaz Ahmad for the Pashto, Northern [pbu] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Sridatta A for fixes to the Hindi [hin], Marathi [mar] and Sanskrit [san] translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Ibrahima Barry and Abdoulaye Barry for the Pular (Adlam) [fuf_adlm] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Elango Cheran, for the (new) Tamil [tam] and Tamil (Sri Lanka) [tam_LK] translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Sascha Brawer, for corrections to many translations and for facilitating new translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Marek Z Jeziorek, for corrections to the Amharic [amh] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Martin Jansche, for corrections to the Mon [mnw] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Yin May Oo, for the Mon [mnw] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Christopher Lwein, for the Manx [glv] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Bivuti Chakma, for the Chakma [ccp] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Daan van Esch and Theresa Breiner, for corrections to multiple translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Jim Brase, for the Tai Dam [blt] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Khun Lein (Sai La Minn), for the Shan [shn] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Sai Zin Di Di Zone, for the Shan [shn] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Yin May Oo, for corrections to the Burmese [mya] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Matthias Bethke, for corrections to the Lao [lao] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The Dzongkha Development Commission of Bhutan, for the Dzongkha [dzo] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Audun Lona, for the Saami, North [sme] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Doug Felt, for corrections to many translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><ulink url='liarumantscha.ch'>Lia Rumantscha</ulink> for the Romansch translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>John Ross for the Cherokee translations [chr_cased] and [char_uppercase].</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>lorjungkoo for the Khün [kkh_lana] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Saadat Mateen, for corrections to the Urdu [urd] translation, and an improved translation Urdu (2) [urd_2].</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Michael Cysouw, for the identification of a few languages.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Philippe Verdy, for suggestions on the site and for the identification of a few languages.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Armin Hoenen, for corrections to the Chokwe [cjk] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Adolfo Jayme Barrientos, for corrections to the Guaraní, Paraguayan [gug] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Lane Schwartz, for corrections to the Latvian [lav] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Rocky Malaviya, for corrections to the Gujarati [guj] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>David Crossland, for corrections to the Gujarati [guj] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>lemzwerg, for corrections to the Greek monotonic [ell_monotonic] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Kang Seonghoon, for corrections to the Khakas [kjh] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Theo Jayaraj Samuel and tradcom.de, for the conversion of the [tel] translation to Unicode.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>c933103, for identifying a Vietnamese translation in the han nom script [vie_han].</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Sungsit Sawaiwan, for identifying an alternate Thai translation [tha2].</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Leo Broukhis, for reporting errors in the map locations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Ken Shirriff, for suggestions on the site.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Philip Jacobs for reporting the incorrect identification of the language of the [qud] and [qxa] translations.</para>
    </listitem>
      
    <listitem>
      <para>Shree Devi Kumar, for corrections to the Bhojpuri [bho] and Magahi [mag] translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Swarup and Atul Thakur, for corrections to the Bengali [ben] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Sriranga and Sathyanarayanarao Magadi Nanjappa, for corrections to the Kannada [kan] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Keshan Sodimana, Pasundu de Silva, for the conversion of the Sinhala [sin] translations to Unicode.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Kevin Scannell for reporting the incorrect identification of the language of the [rmy] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Michael Everson for help with African languages.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Geetha Sambasivam for corrections to the Tamil translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Miguel Sousa for providing the Portuguese government
      translation for Portuguese (Portugal), and the conversion of the
      Yi and Veps translations to Unicode.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Jelena Prokic for corrections to both Serbian transalations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>M Hasan Jowher for the complete Urdu translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Werner Fröhlich for facilitating the Urdu translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>George Myers for noticing a mislabelling of the Yakut
      translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Doug Ewell for corrections to the Seraiki and Serbian
      (latin) translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Andrew Miller for noticing some typos in the site.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Thomas Pace and the National Council for the Maltese
      Language (<ulink
      url='www.kunsilltalmalti.gov.mt'>www.kunsilltalmalti.gov.mt</ulink>),
      for many corrections to the Maltese translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Albrecht Dreiheller for reporting problems on the Maltese
      translation, and noticing that the Sanskrit translation was
      labelled with the wrong region.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Marion Gunn for suggesting clarifications on the use of
      language names.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Arthur Reutenauer for the full Altai, Southern, Shor,
      Evenki, Khakas, Yakut, Tuva, Ojibwa (Northwestern), Inuktitut
      (Eastern Canadian), Kirghiz, Swampy Cree, Tatar, Ticuna,
      Turkmen, and Uyghur (Arabic) translations; the first article for
      the Assyrian Neo-Aramaic, Dzongha, Mongolian (Mongolian), Tamang
      and Yi translations, the repair of the Belarusan, Bosnian
      (Cyrillic), Bulgarian, Mongol, Latvian, Kazakh Macedonian,
      Osetin, Siona and Serbian translations; corrections to the
      German, Italian and Nepali translations; and help with the
      Slovenian translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Emmanuel Vallois for the conversion of the Colorado and
      Venda translations to Unicode.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Miikka-Markus Alhonen for corrections to the Tajik,
      Finnish, Azerbaijani, North (Latin), Azerbaijani, North
      (Cyrillic) translations, major corrections to the Uzbek
      translations, finding and correcting the Turkmen (Latin)
      translation, and typing the Assyrian Neo-Aramaic
      translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>http://www.freewebs.com/turkmenweb/bmgninjarnamasy.htm for
      the Turkmen (Latin) [tuk_latn] translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>http://gddc.pt for the (Crioulo da Guin&#x00E9;) [008],
      (Kimbundo) [009], Makhuwa [vmw], (Tetum) [010], Umbundo [011]
      translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>&#x0628;&#x0647;&#x0646;&#x0627;&#x0645;
      &#x0627;&#x0633;&#x0641;&#x0647;&#x0628;&#x062F; (Behnam
      Esfahbod) for major corrections to the Farsi, Western
      translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Wunna Ko Ko for corrections to the Myanmar translation, and for
      conversion to the Unicode 5.1 format.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>User "transtic" on the Asia Finest Discussion Forum.</para>
    </listitem>


    <listitem>
      <para>Roey Horns for noticing typos in the German translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Dr. Ramanand Jha 'Raman' for translating the UDHR in Maithili</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Pandit Govinda Jha for reviewing the Maithili translation</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Anshuman Pandey for facilitating the Maithili translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Tombekai V. Sherman for translating the UDHR in Vai and providing
      the XML representation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Charles Riley, for facilitating the Vai translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Marcin Kowalczyk for corrections to the Polish translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Mojca Miklavec for help with the Slovenian translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Sahak Petrosyan for a major review of the Armenian
      translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Otto Stolz for corrections to the German translation (1901
      orthography) and for providing a translation following the 1996
      orthography.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Asmus Freytag for help with the German translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Dan Alexandru for corrections to the Romanian translations
      (1953 and 1993 orthographies) and providing a translation
      following the 2006 orthography.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Henning Brunzel for noticing the mislabeling of the 
      Cashinahua translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>&#x0404;&#x0432;&#x0433;&#x0435;&#x043D;&#x0456;&#x0439;
      &#x041C;&#x0435;&#x0449;&#x0435;&#x0440;&#x044F;&#x043A;&#x043E;&#x0432;
      (Eugeniy Meshcheryakov) for corrections to the Ukrainian
      translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Sholem Berger and Raphael Finkel for providing the Yiddish
      translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Benjamin Titze for noticing small differences between the
      official record of the Declaration and our English version.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Mihai Ni&#x021B;&#x0103; for correcting the Romanian
      translation (1953 orthography) and providing a translation
      following the 1993 orthography.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Daniel Yacob for providing the Amharic translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Martin Hosken for help with the Myanmar translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Don Osborn, <ulink url='bisharat.net'/>, for providing a
      vastly improved Hausa translation, in both Niger and Nigeria
      orthographies.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Zden&#x011B;k Wagner for proofreading and correcting many
      spelling mistakes in the Czech translation and in the Hindi
      translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>António Martins for pointing out the <ulink
      url='http://linguarium.iling-ran.ru'>Linguarium</ulink>
      project.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Leandro Reis for proofreading and correcting the
      Portuguese (Portugal) translation, pointing at a source for the
      Portuguese (Brazil) translation, and proofreading it.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Na&#x00E7;&#x00F5;es Unidas no Brazil for providing the
      text of the Portuguese (Brazil) translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Yannis Haralambous, <ulink
      url='http://www.polytoniko.gr/'/>, for providing the Greek
      (polytonic) version.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Aung for the full Burmese version, and Craig
      Rublee for facilitating that.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Dirk Meyer for help with the German translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Patrick Andries, John Hudson, Kent Karlsson, Jonathan Kew,
      Erik van der Poel for comments on the representation of
      <emphasis>&#x2019;n</emphasis> in Afrikaans.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Patrick Hall for suggesting to create plain text and html
      versions of the &#x201C;first article&#x201D;-only documents,
      and for help with the Themne translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Valaxay Dalaloy via the Language
      Observatory for the full Lao translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Allen Bailochan Tuladhar via the Language Observatory for
      a good chunck of the Nepali translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Kumari Co Ltd. via the Language Observatory for the full
      Marathi, Gujarati, Seraiki, Bengali, Kannada and Western Panjabi
      translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Chuluun Erdenebat and Ulziibat Batbaatar via the Language
      Observatory for the full Mongolian (Cyrillic) translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
       <para>Jun Sugawara via the Language Observatory for the full
       Uighur (Latin).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>the <ulink
      url='http://gii2.nagaokaut.ac.jp/gii/blog/lopdiary.php'>Language
      Observatory</ulink> for having initiated an effort similar to ours.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Andrew Cunningham for pointing out the existence of the
      <ulink
      url='http://gii2.nagaokaut.ac.jp/gii/blog/lopdiary.php'>Language
      Observatory</ulink> and its conversion of some translations of the
      UDHR; for working on the Igbo translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Andrew West for pointing out the presence of the Yi, Sichuan on
      the OHCHR web site.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Sukhjinder Sidhu for pointing out the mixing of Panjabi,
      Eastern and Panjabi, Western.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Jyothis Edathoot at Jyothis.net for typing the Malayalam
      translation from the OHCHR source.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>K. Kalyanasundaram for typing the Tamil translation from the
      OHCHR source.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Jony Rosenne helped with the proper HTML usage for
      right-to-left texts.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Niti Hantaweepant (&#x0E19;&#x0E34;&#x0E18;&#x0E34;
      &#x0E2B;&#x0E32;&#x0E0D;&#x0E17;&#x0E27;&#x0E35;&#x0E1E;&#x0E31;&#x0E19;&#x0E18;&#x0E38;&#x0E4C;)
      and Ornnida Muneepeerakul
      (&#x0E2D;&#x0E23;&#x0E19;&#x0E34;&#x0E14;&#x0E32;
      &#x0E21;&#x0E38;&#x0E19;&#x0E35;&#x0E1E;&#x0E35;&#x0E23;&#x0E30;&#x0E01;&#x0E38;&#x0E25;)
      for typing the Thai translation from the OHCHR source.</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
      <para>Rani Mahapatra for (partially) deciphering the Bengali image provided
      by the OHCHR site.</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
      <para>Simon Ager at <ulink
      url='http://www.omniglot.com'>omniglot.com</ulink> for gathering
      a few translations of the first article of the UDHR.</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
      <para>Adobe Systems, for providing the XML files for 280
      languages (pre-review); for corrections to the
      Catalan-Valencian-Balear [cat] and Vietnamese [vie]
      translations.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Eric Muller, for initiating and coordinating this
      project.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

<!--
  <bridgehead id='fonts'>Fonts</bridgehead>

  <para>Many thanks to the font designers and foundries who made fonts
  available on generous terms. We believe that all the fonts we use
  are available without a fee for everyone working on this project; if
  we misinterpreted a license, please let us know and accept our
  apologies. See <ulink url='tech_files.html#pdf'>here</ulink> for
  a list of the fonts we use.</para>

-->

  <bridgehead id='corrections'>Corrections</bridgehead>

  <para>If we did not record your contribution (sorry!), or
  you would like a different wording, please <ulink
  url='contacts.html'>let us know</ulink>.</para>
  
</article>

