<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<article>
  <title>How can I help?</title>
  
  <para>If you want to help with a language, your first task is to
  read these guidelines, identify what needs to be done for that
  language, and what you are willing to do. If the task is sizeable,
  please send us an email, so that we can coordinate and avoid
  duplication of effort; we&#x2019;ll get you in touch with other
  folks who have volunteered for that language.</para>

  <para>If you want to help with the overall project, please send us
  an email. At this point, we do not anticipate that there will be a
  lot of general work, but we&#x2019;ll let you know if that turns out
  not to be the case.</para>

  <para>You can send comments, questions, contributions by email to
udhr at efele.net. </para>

  <para>You can also submit pull requests to the Github repository <ulink url='http://efele.net/eric-muller/udhr'>eric-muller/udhr</ulink>.</para>


  <bridgehead>My language is not listed, or it is in stage 1.</bridgehead>
  
  <para>This means that we do not have an existing translation, from
  any source, in any form. Your task is to find an authoritative
  translation, which will presumably be on paper. You should provide a
  copy to this project (a good scan by email, a good photocopy or an
  original by mail), as well as a precise description of your
  source. If there is no known translation, then you can provide one,
  but again make sure that you identify the translator as clearly as
  possible. In both cases, you also want to identify the language
  using the <ulink url='http://www.ethnologue.com'>Ethnologue
  codes</ulink>, as well as the dialect if that is relevant.</para>

  <bridgehead>My language is in stage 2 or 3.</bridgehead>

  <para>This means that we have a source document, but it has not been
  turned into XML, or only partially. Your task is to type it in a
  computer. Ideally, you would provide the XML form, using one of the
  Unicode UTFs (numeric character entities are fine). However, if you
  do not feel comfortable with XML, a simple plain text version will
  do just as well, as long as there are enough traces of the preamble,
  articles, etc., so that we can add the XML markup; please use one of
  the UTFs or an encoding that can be converted reliably and easily
  to Unicode (e.g. ISO 8859-x is ok, but ISCII is out).</para>

  <para>If you believe that the source has a typo, please type both
  what the source has and your suggested correction like this:
  &#x201C;miskate [mistake]&#x201D;. The goal of this stage is
  primarily to represent the source accurately, and only secondarily
  to correct it.</para>

  <bridgehead>My language is in stage 4.</bridgehead>

  <para>We have an XML version, and it is reasonably complete.</para>

  <para>You can check the Github issues, to see if there is known
  problem you can fix.</para>

  <para>If you spot an issue in the text, you can alert us, or better
  you can create a Github issue. And if you know how to fix it, you
  can tell us, or better you create a Github pull request.</para>

  <para>One aspect is to replace the ambiguous characters such as
  U+0027 &#x0027; APOSTROPHE or U+002D &#x002D; HYPHEN-MINUS by less
  ambiguous alternatives (for U+0027, U+02BC &#x02BC; MODIFIER LETTER
  APOSTROPHE or U+2019 &#x2019; RIGHT SINGLE QUOTATION MARK). This is
  actually a bit more tricky than it sounds, because we need to find a
  balance between using the &#x201C;best&#x201D; character and
  actually reflecting the common practice. For example, it could be
  that a language&#x2019;s orthography uses an apostrophe-like symbol
  to write a global stop, in which case U+02BC &#x02BC; MODIFIER
  LETTER APOSTROPHE is the &#x201C;best&#x201D; character; but if the
  orthography does not use an apostrophe-like symbol for another
  purpose, it may very well be that the common practice is to use
  U+0027 &#x0027; APOSTROPHE.</para>

  <bridgehead>Audio and Video recording</bridgehead>

  <para>You may also consider helping with a <ulink url='http://udhr.video/'>video or audio recording</ulink>.</para>

</article>

